hello and welcome everyone this is
active guest stream 15.3 lucky number
three with Bobby
we're here with Bobby azarian as well as
some guests we're going to have a
discussion
talk about a range of different topics
it's June 1st 2023
first Adam and Michael can introduce
themselves then Bobby will pass it off
to you for sharing your screen and
facilitating this however you see fit so
Adam go for it
hello uh I'm Adam I am a research fellow
at the Johns Hopkins Center for
psychedelic and Consciousness research
um long standing interest in the free
energy principle
um Consciousness Free Will psychedelics
artificial intelligence and along the
way I met and befriended Bobby and
um
uh I guess uh
proud to be part of the movement so
thanks for coming Adam yeah Adam
I wish we would have time to get into
this today but Adam is uh presented a
pretty clear mechanistic model of Free
Will cybernetic Free Will and um
there's just this huge problem where and
I'll keep this short we're gonna
introduce Michael but um
basically the the main kind of straw man
against free will is that there's this
argument that you have this non-physical
mind doing like stuff outside of
causality and that's why everyone's
rejecting it as not a scientific idea
but
of course something can't work if it's
not it doesn't have mechanism it's not
real it's not real so it's kind of a
ridiculous debate to have if you want to
talk about what people are talking about
when they discuss Free Will in the past
we didn't have mechanisms to understand
what that was but now we understand
things like top-down causation we
understand control and when you have
that language you can actually talk
about what free will is in a mechanistic
way and that just changes the debate
completely
um that's not enough to convince people
that you know there's something called
free will because there's a lot of
issues that we get into but Adam's one
of the people that have been taking this
nebulous concept and have have been
trying to show that there's actually a
very specific set of mechanisms and it's
nothing outside of science but it is
science that is outside of our current
Paradigm it's it's just dynamics that we
don't normally that weren't included in
the previous model so it looks like
magic but it's actually there's stuff
going on there
um so yeah uh we're gonna have a longer
discussion with Adam in the future
either on my Channel or maybe we'll come
back and make it all about free will
because it's such a big topic but yeah
thanks for coming
and invite Michael as well so
um
am I supposed to take the wheel now yeah
obviously I'm a fan of Bobby's
um I very much like uh
oh well I think it's important I think
the the work that uh Bobby is trying to
articulate and Adam I'm a fan uh so this
is the first time we've met but I've
watched some of your stuff as well and
and Daniel obviously we've talked
um and uh yeah let's just uh yield to
Bobby and let's see where we go here
um yeah Michael has a background in kind
of um system science and those kind of
things that's how he kind of resonate is
um kind of like the system science
approach but thinking about how system
science can be applied to like
psychology and organizational issues so
how to make this stuff that's very
theoretical practical and so we're kind
of working on that on the side and then
Brennan Grand MC will be coming and
joining the conversation since he's not
here right now I'll just give a little
introduction for him he's the author of
a book called emergentism and he has a
Facebook group called meta modern
spirituality and basically he's in that
book he's turned this emergence Paradigm
which is basically kind of the opposite
of the productionist Paradigm
um into something like a sort of secular
religion and
um so he's talking about a lot of these
same things
um so he'll join us shortly probably I
think he's watching the the stream and
is trying to get into the zoom link
um
so yeah we can start I um
it'd be great to for this to be sort of
a discussion so if anything
I say
triggers any sort of thoughts or
criticisms please speak up because I
don't have an organized uh set of slides
and there's a lot to talk about and the
problem really when I was trying to make
these slides was like everything I say
kind of gets into something else and so
I had like a hundred slides and I was
just trying to organize them in the last
minute so
um I think you know I have some slides
that were made in the past for other
presentations that are just going to be
kind of like a road map but
um we can Veer off of that and I'm going
to be saying a lot of stuff that's not
in the slides
um
yeah so I guess we can start
so I'll share my screen because I just
shared my screen for my computer and I
couldn't see you but I think that uh
trick to that is to share my screen
through Zoom
and then share do like slideshow and
then I should be able to see your faces
on the side yep okay so you can see my
screen now
yeah
then if I do slideshow it doesn't work
yeah perfect
okay
um so
uh Bobby just before you get started I
believe Brennan's joined us as well hey
Brandon
you've warmed up the crowd those audios
yeah his audience probably not connected
yet but um
yeah so we can just begin uh hey Brandon
I introduced you and uh yeah I was just
on the YouTube uh version and then I got
the link so great it's a pleasure to be
here thanks for uh thanks for the
introduction appreciate it
yeah no problem please feel free to like
chime in at any time because I really
need help here I'm not like prepared to
do this by myself so
um
and maybe you can play the role of the
critic too because I should have invited
some like anti-free will people because
um or just some Skeptics of these ideas
because
what I realized is like
I'm saying these things a lot of them
were the things in my book The Romance
of reality and
I make that argument as clear as I can
but then people have criticisms that for
whatever reason you know how I worded it
don't address those and then they're not
convinced and then I do nothing to
convince anyone who doesn't already
believe this so it's actually a lot more
um fruitful if there's a sort of this
dialectical debate like this dynamic
because then you hear both sides and
then I can actually address the things
that people think are the issues that
might
um
you know cast out on some of the things
that I'm arguing so
um the teleological stance so this is
the name of the self-help system for a
lack of a better uh term I know people
hear self-help and they think uh you
know that's something like cheesy and
new age or you know BS and there are a
lot of like you know snake oil salesmen
in this place and I think that's why
it's so important that we try if
possible to create something like a
self-help system and you know
something almost like a religion like
something that has practices
and a sort of instruction manual for a
living
um based on scientific principles now it
doesn't have to be based on you know
science won't explain everything
um or address everything
um but this provides a foundation where
we can
actually start to build a logic where we
can go some of these things are right
and some of these things aren't and we
can start to see things that have been
said
in folk psychology or New Age practices
that people just considered to be
non-scientific or pseudoscience we can
see how that maps on to some of these
newer mechanisms that we're
understanding because now we're starting
to look at biology and neuroscience and
psychology from the perspective of
information Theory and thermodynamics
and these are
like revealing new mechanisms that I
believe can create a bridge between
reductionist science and
the higher Sciences but also a lot of
these statements you'll hear you know
things that you hear in like spiritual
circles or people are doing practices or
uh and you know just different little
things that they find to be very
effective in most cases there's a
scientific explanation for why those
things are effective and most
science-minded people are ignoring all
that stuff so they're like throwing out
all of these things that emerge because
they were adaptations like practices
um you know community building things
like that are just completely being
ignored
um and that's really bad it's just
throwing the baby out with the bath
water and as long as we
have that mentality
um you know scientists they may say you
know I don't want to
promote religion organize religion let's
say or you know like kind of new age
spirituality I don't want to promote
that but they're actually helping keep
those things
in existence because the a lot of
regular people are hearing this
scientific worldview that's the
mainstream world view and it's very
nihilistic in some of its beliefs and
that'd be okay if that's how reality was
but we're going to see that a lot of
these are based on mistaken assumptions
and people are rejecting that worldview
because it's doesn't offer anything of
value to them as a normal person and
they will opt for other less
evidence-based uh World Views or
philosophies because they're not getting
that from that so
science is actually helping like
pseudoscience and things like that
um if they want to keep science isolated
from all these practical things and sort
of addressing bigger existential and
even spiritual questions and so if we
can do that if we can build that bridge
it would be good for unifying everyone
but it would also cut down on a lot of
the the pseudoscience and stuff that
people are trying to
um kind of prevent from you know not
going there but actually I think that's
um part of the problem if that makes any
sense
um
so this is stuff for my sub stack road
to Omega go there and check it out
there's uh uh post on the teleological
stance that break this down in uh more
detail then I'll be able to give here
today
um I have this word in the slide poetic
meta naturalism if you're familiar with
my book
um you might have seen that it's not
really important
um to really talk about why I call it
that but let's just say there are these
two distinctive worldviews so there's
the old mainstream scientific world view
which is the reductionist world view
which I think is basically a nihilistic
world view
um and uh there are a lot of assumptions
built into this world view based on
just we had limited knowledge at the
time of how the world works so there
were things like for example when we
thought the world was Newtonian you just
couldn't get away from determinism uh
this kind of strict laplacian
determinism LaPlace basically took
Newton's
um kind of framework and tried to apply
it to everything it's really interesting
that Newton himself didn't do that he
didn't think that his laws applied to
life and Newton was actually very
religious and thought there were all
these crazy hidden messages in the Bible
which is neat and kind of like covered
up because people you know don't want
people to know that that Newton was so
religious but um
so LaPlace kind of you know created this
deterministic philosophy and when we
thought that was the truth and there was
no room for a human agency there was
just one future trajectory and we
couldn't do anything to change that and
we couldn't
we were we weren't really doing anything
to begin with it was all everything we
do is sort of illusory and we can talk
about determinism in Greater detail
um but that's one nihilistic aspect is
that we don't have any agency and we
don't have free will free will it's a
bit more of a loaded term there's just
assumptions with that word like with the
word free that uh make it a little bit
more of a contentious subject but um
yeah without with determinism in the
strict sense
no one could have any agency so it kind
of if you accept that scientific
um
proposition then you're like basically
accepting that you have no control over
the future or your life and that can be
very depressing and demotivating in
their studies that we can talk about
that have shown that
um that belief actually causes people to
for example
um behave less morally they will be more
likely to cheat
uh because they don't have culpability
because no one's responsible for
anything that's then basically
choosing
to not have this agency that I'll
explain exactly what I mean by that but
basically I mean the fact that you can
tell them that and then they lose it and
then they start behaving more immorally
it's obvious that there's something
causal there that's changing their
behavior
so that's kind of a clue that that
pictured something doesn't make sense
there
um
and it also causes people to be like
really depressed and have kind of
existential meltdowns
um I personally had you know when I
thought determinism was the only
explanation that made sense I sort of
had you know times where I would have
these experiences where I was very
disturbed by the fact that I had no
control over anything and that this was
sort of a tape that was determined from
the initial event and that I was just
playing that out it can be very
disturbing if you take this stuff
seriously and what I'm arguing is that a
lot of the scientists preaching this
stuff they're not taking it seriously
because they can't it would be your life
would just be over if you really
believed that you had no agency because
you would stop doing stuff
um
seriously and uh it took me out for a
good two years
um how do you even take it seriously
like what does that do what do you do
then
okay
um so the it happened
um it was a combination of reading the
this book um the meme machine
um by Susan Blackmore and um Darwin's
dangerous idea there's this one sentence
that just like took me out it was like
um everything up to this moment
including your genes environment uh and
all your experiences including the first
half of the sentence will determine how
you uh interpret the second episode it
was sort of like just this web of
causation being described on a different
level of analysis sort of like bringing
that to the foreground and I was like
and not seeing me in that foreground and
and then I was like oh hey there isn't
like a neuron in my brain that knows or
cares that I exist this whole or and
then was wait not even a wait so sodium
ions are going to sodium ion they're
just gonna follow those gradients like
oh God and I so
um and it just sort of had me and and so
for I just was
I mean so it's like I was actually so
for a while as um uh
is it kind of paralyze you or do you
just go I'm gonna do what I was gonna do
anyway but I'm gonna do it I'm gonna
have this weird sort of you know
experience at the same time because it's
all meaningless I'm just going to go
through life I'm probably going to look
really sad but I'm gonna do everything
that I plan to do otherwise or does it
just shut you down where you're like I'm
not gonna get out of bed
there was kind of like a double
Consciousness about it too because it
was like I'd be moving between like um
like
having that as a as a frame and but then
like to take action you're like you
can't you can't you just gotta throw it
out the window and so like yeah so in
some on occasion there would be kind of
like a
um maybe this is a I don't think it took
me in an unethical Direction but
um kind of like a like a fracket mindset
like uh well
it doesn't nothing matters anyway so woo
but yeah and it won't really stick for
me can can I offer a devil's advocate
take here and yeah I don't know if we're
I don't know if we're derailing or no
this is perfect this is great but um so
and it is very much a devil's advocate
position because I think Bobby you and I
are very much aligned on trying to
emphasize the importance of uh free will
the the causal power of information
potentially Etc I'm sure you might get
into some of that uh but I will say this
in its favor or in in addition to what's
being said
um so I also had an experience like that
of suffering from the uh you know
seeming implications of the
deterministic universe but I do think
that there's a way of also allowing all
of that to be the case and responding
differently and there are a number of
different ways that that can look
um I mean there's the nietzschean
approach to this which is actually kind
of taking this deterministic cycle and
kind of the Eternal recurrence of the
same as sort of a wild guessing to
existence
um and I'll just I'll just throw that
out there and bracket it we could come
back to that one uh what do you mean by
that though sorry I I don't know so
Nietzsche was he would philosophize
while walking or he would think his
philosophy while going on these long
walks and everything right and one day
he was walking in the Swiss Alps and he
sees this gigantic Rock
um and uh he comes to this sudden
realization
um and I guess I won't get into the
whole story because it would probably be
a little bit too much but basically the
the realization that Springs there which
he uh which he has when at this sort of
like monolithic scene is somehow he sort
of transported and appreciates that
um what what he would need to do was
affirm his existence uh under the
assumption that everything that has
happened and will happen uh will happen
over and over and over again for
eternity all the mistakes all the
ecstasies ETC it was all there almost
you could kind of think of it kind of in
the uh you know there's the big bang big
crunch model and then it repeats and so
let's say something like that is
happening where yeah he called it
Eternal recurrence right I mean yeah
yeah yeah a return of recurrence and he
basically said that um we need to be
able to positively affirm that in an
exuberant sense uh and and actually and
here's like what is that Queen well what
it means is that if you take the idea
seriously
um that this is your life and you are
therefore radically responsible in some
ways for what you experience
um uh and I'll come back to this in the
sense of what responsibility could mean
in this context as well
um then then it actually imbues
everything with an incredible
significance because this is what you'll
be experiencing over and over again uh
the second thing I wanted to say which I
think might kind of preempt some of your
kind of like well how does that work how
can you be responsible uh is um I do
think that there's a phenomenological
way that you can uh come to terms with
determinism uh that basically
concludes something like okay even if
mechanistically this can be describable
in terms of deterministic cause and
effect all the way back
my experience of it is rather different
I have the experience of free will I I
feel as though as if I can choose as I
want to uh and so there's no necessary
reason why some descriptive uh you know
framework needs to it needs to impinge
upon my own phenomenological sense of
reality so for a long time I made peace
with this question that way by basically
saying yeah it's all determined but I
feel as though I have free will and
that's really I think the the core there
because um let me yeah let me say
something about that and I don't want it
to be seem dismissive
um but I mean this is not your idea
anyway so I don't really have to
apologize to you it's Nichi and it's one
of the possible things that I think
you're considering but I mean I I you
know we've talked about this I think you
kind of we have similar ideas about
agency what I want to say about that is
basically that is
similar to compatibilism and what's
going on is that these people are
there's language Games first of all like
if you want to talk about that if you
believe that causal story
in the strict sense
um and it's more complicated at because
I'm saying that the the there is
causality there's always cause and
effect to everything and that doesn't
not permit agency but what I'm going to
say is the the the kind of magic
ingredient to understanding how this can
be uh you know uh mechanistic idea
um our mechanistic process How Free Will
can be explained as part of the causal
chain uh we need to talk about top-down
causation and that's really the game
changer and but without top down
causation I don't think there is any
responsibility and what I think that
Nietzsche and others are doing is
they're first of all they're
compartmentalizing they're like they're
they're they're they're not fully taking
the determinism they're talking about
seriously and if you do that like you
you have to compartmentalize if you
believe that because like Adam said like
you have to
throw that out when you actually want to
take action so first of all everybody
who believes in determinism is kind of
living a split personality life and that
that leads to all kinds of cognitive
dissonance
but it's worse than that all of oh I
mean you still are I mean in a way it
depends so like
um I'm agnostic about determinism in
terms of like that was part of but it
wasn't agnosticism about determinism but
going more deflationary on causation or
more instrumentalists on causation and I
I do think that but I'm open to there
being like a best causal handling or
like there could be like a new like um
Gestalt ship for me where like causation
kind of like enters into physics and
like full majesty and like that's what
this is that's that's what I want to
describe but the move for me was um
compatibilism via instrumental causation
that kind of stays within it as like
carols like it stays in its Lane yes and
I I so
I will put out a thing out there where
you could have determinism and have a
true agency too at these higher levels
you would still need top-down causation
but you might not need any indeterminism
at the most fundamental level uh like
Quantum and determinism
um and you could still have uh
potentially agency and that's sort of
Adam's perspective or like he says he's
agnostic on it but
um in the future I hope to convince Adam
that there's a better solution and so so
what I was saying to Brendan is that
these are language games when he's like
uh it's truly this way you know it's
this way but that should make you feel
like you're responsible because this is
you know the life you have and the One
You're Gonna repair whatever you know
I'm it's good reasoning Brian Green says
similar stuff and that's why I say this
Brian Green's like the decision is real
but it's not really you making it but
it's a real like a lot of strange weird
language games that if you actually make
language the focus which I wanted to do
but it's way too abstract like I didn't
have time to nail that down for today
but that's what I want to do in the
future and you can show that people who
are talking about this stuff especially
people who are you know trying to find
some sort of Silver Lining to
determinism they're they're using words
inconsistently they will use a word one
way and then contradict it they might
even use the same word in two different
ways
um in the same sentence but basically
you can't have well I'm gonna let you
respond Brandon but I don't think there
can be in his that that model any true
responsibility and then this solution of
like but I feel like I have it to me it
doesn't give you anything additional
like you're just an epic phenomenon and
to me that can be almost worse like he's
given a nice spin on the a positive way
you can see it but there's other people
like illusionists that say you know we
have this phenomenal experience it feels
like I have free will but there's
absolutely no responsibility like Sam
Harris was like I don't have pride uh a
friend was just talking to me about this
because he's a Sam Harris fan but he's
turned off by this whole no free will
thing and then he hears Sam Harris
contradict himself all the time because
Sam Harris will say you don't have Free
Will and the whole thing is on Free Will
and then there's a little commercial for
his podcast where he goes you have the
freedom to choose to listen to this
podcast and it's like you're you're
using double talk like constantly so
it's very notable Sam Harris does not
tell that to his daughter
and he tells he says
they say to each other but he says I'm
not I'm not going to tell my kids
because it's going to make them you know
behave differently and like all these
bad things that I said but when they
grow up I'll tell them that they don't
have any agency when they're ready for
it but what I'm saying is all of that is
absolutely ridiculous talk it's
absolutely nonsense to be like
she doesn't have age I'm I'm not gonna
tell like everything he's doing is it
like the whole argument's completely
self-defeating in every way and there's
a lot of people that have tried to make
nice stories out of it but ultimately
they're contradicting themselves and
compat compatibilism in its current form
is a contradiction and people call it
out for that all the time
um but that doesn't stop the compatibles
because it seems like the best answer it
goes yeah but I experienced this agency
so it has to be real on some level but
then how can we go against this
determinism it seems to go against
causality in general so it's like
a lot of people like Dan didn't their
solution was like you know I'm not going
to go against
um these sorts of like you know I'm not
gonna go against uh determinism or
causality which I'm saying it doesn't go
against causality but they think the
best solution is to try to do some magic
and make both these things work together
um yeah so we can talk more about that
but yeah maybe you have a response that
please yeah yeah I was just gonna throw
in
um you know something that we had
grounded this in before was the idea
that uh you know we choose not to act on
on the back of that right so there's
that balance of you know what I'm
talking about right yeah yeah if you yes
if you believe that it's going to affect
your behavior too and what I'm gonna
argue is that you won't exercise your
agency as much as you would
uh
uh if you don't believe it
um along those lines part of what really
concerns me about the
um
anti-free will rhetoric is because like
an agency like so like active inference
that like Carl sometimes say like you
know there's certain optimism that's
required like that's just built into it
for the way you pursue goals by um
predicting them into being and so like
if you don't pers if you're not if you
stop believing in yourself as a cause
being able to predict certain goals that
actually could be a real problem I
believe it is a real problem and that
actually these people living this are
already not behaving optimally not
making decisions optimally here's the
thing that you may see Sam here is a
really successful guy how do you explain
that it's because he's living to he he
has a split personality the part of him
that believe like is like plumped about
doing all this stuff it's disconnected
from the part of him that really
believes that he has no agency
um and you've seen that in those studies
where they will like you see people lose
that belief and it changes their
behavior so my point is if if that's the
way reality is and we have to tell the
truth that's what Sam Harris says like
I'm not going to sugarcoat it for you
but what I'm saying is that idea is
built on a mountain of language
ambiguities that are creating this
problem and
um just a misunderstanding of of
causation because if you think all
causation is bottom up which means that
the system is not there's no higher
level control
um and this is kind of getting into
details that I need to give some more
background for but if it's all bottom-up
causation then there is no room for
agency but if you have top-down
causation and the whole system is this
control center
um it's a cybernetic control system
that's basically
um
um we can explain this later but what I
will argue is that the evolutionary
process
um accumulates knowledge uh so adaptive
information in
um biological systems so predictive
information about the environment the
knowledge the adaptations that are being
acquired through Evolution correspond to
um jeans and
um you know neural connections that
um
uh basically encode information about
the external world and that's what
starts to give a system agency
um and that's why living systems behave
differently than inanimate systems and
um that is because the system has gained
causal power so the system as a coherent
unit
um is starting to control the components
that it's made of and the trajectory
that the system follows
um and so for example Philip ball is a
journalist who's been writing about this
a lot like one of the most respected
science journalists but if you drop a
pigeon and a rock off a tower The Rock
You can predict with Newtonian uh
mechanics you can with with classical
physics equations You can predict the
trajectory of the rock you can't predict
the trajectory of the bird so there's
something fundamentally different about
those two things and I'm saying that
behavioral distinction is what we have
to call agency now that doesn't give us
get us to free will but it shows us that
there's some sort of causal difference
between biological systems and inanimate
systems and this used to be attributed
to vitalism what I'm saying is that
vitalism wasn't necessarily wrong we
just didn't know what that vital force
was and now we have a name for it and we
call it information
um so I kind of veered from the point
maybe but um yeah what was uh
I can't remember what I was answering
with that
um
yeah go ahead yeah so maybe we should
finish up the Nietzsche thing and then I
should get into some slides and then we
should uh come back to this yeah I was
just gonna say real quick again I think
Bobby I think what you're articulating I
mean having read your book and you know
talked with you a lot about your work I
think we're very much on the same page
uh I was very much also at the same time
doing a devil's advocate thing though
for a couple of reasons and it would it
would derail us too much from the
present topic which is more important
than trying to make a devil's advocate a
case living with determinism so yeah
well I
I told Daniel that I'm a recovering
determinist that's kind of that's kind
of what I want to do here because I said
if you don't if we don't hear the
criticism then the people who don't
agree with this I'm not gonna answer so
you said that yeah I would just like to
push you a little bit more to explain
yeah if if it's purely deterministic
what's where's the responsibility that
Nietzsche is talking about yeah well let
me say maybe a couple things too
um uh that adds further context here
um there's sort of a tradition uh
uh of
let's say
using historical uh philosophical or
even theological categories
um and the kind of uh Frameworks that
those used to provide for making sense
of really important
um Concepts and ways of being in the
world and then presuming that if someone
deviated from those that there would be
these natural natural necessary sort of
implications that would flow from
thinking differently about something uh
the classic case in my experience has
been oh we need morality and moral facts
to make us good people as soon as you
don't believe in moral facts you'll
become you know a a terrible human being
and that's not true uh you know people
who don't believe in moral facts in the
kind of traditional way uh can find all
sorts of groundings for their yeah but
sorry to interrupt but I do I can see
like these language things going on like
everywhere in these discussions so for
example
um
yeah so
you're saying that people don't need
morality and that these people but then
you said traditional morality so that
was the point I was going to make is
that the people who let's say you don't
believe that there's any
purposefulness in nature there's no
teleologies there's like everything's
random and accidental
then they go well you know what that
doesn't make me depressed I'm actually
this is the only time I'm you know this
is all we've got so I better make it
count there's no afterlife
um so what I'm saying is they're still
deriving morals from this uh Paradigm
and they're actually deriving meaning
and purposeful principles out of this so
they're really
um
um in a way there they still see some
they're they're still finding what they
need to find to
um behave in an optimal way but what I'm
saying is that that's kind of a
teleological View and they're not fully
sticking to their Paradigm with no
assumptions they're building on lots of
assumptions and you get this morality
that ends up looking exactly like
religion once you map it out and you go
oh yeah like the golden rule for example
the Golden Rule you don't need a
religion or the Golden Rule you just
need to know that you're an agent there
are other agents like you they're like
you they also experience happiness and
suffering therefore I'm going to treat
them like I would want to be treated and
also there's an incentive to do that
because then they can treat me that way
um then they'll treat me as I've treated
them but the Golden Rule could be a
basis for a religion and a moral
postulate so are they really moral
morally free free of moral facts are are
they creating a set of morals from
a paradigm that's supposed to be
completely moral free but maybe it's not
because what I'm saying basically is
they're kind of
converging on this kind of purposeful
narrative without even realizing it well
yeah I mean there's a there's a lot
there I mean I would say what you're
getting at which is important which is
there's often a performative
contradiction that we're engaged in
we're asserting something logically and
then our our actions are sort of you
know suggesting otherwise I mean if I if
I'm a solipsist and I say you know I
believe in solipsism and I think this is
right it's sort of like well wait why
are you telling me that you know like uh
so there's there's that element to it uh
there are actually though some rather
detailed arguments you could make that
get into things like
um well yes I'm a solipsist but I'm
talking to you about it because your
projection of me and it's still
worthwhile for me to have projections
with my you know conversational
projections to myself Etc and there are
versions of that for the free will sort
of a thing right that's you could but I
think there's fallacies with all of that
so for example let's say and there's a a
old joke about
the teacher gives a a lecture on
solipsism and why solipsism can't be
refuted and the student comes up to him
after the lecture and says oh you're a
solipsist too like he's happy to meet
another solipsist but the whole point is
that the other person doesn't exist so
you're very happy to meet yourself but
so what I would say is let's follow that
anytime okay so then we would do a
little game where we break that down or
what I'm saying when you start to break
all those things down they lead you back
to the same road so let's say you're not
real Brendan you're a projection of my
mind but what does that mean
Brendan is a projection of my mind but
you're an agent and you have different
beliefs than me as I know myself here
and you're going to do things you're
going to behave in ways that are
different than I would
then I would behave because you have a
different set of beliefs ultimately
compared to actually the me I know even
if you're really me what I'm saying is
that really me
doesn't really have any meaning because
when you start to Define you as this
agent even if you make this metaphysical
claim that you're a projection of me
for all practical purposes you are an
agent within this system that has a
different set of beliefs than what I
know that behaves differently so what
I'm saying is even the thought
experiment has this language fall
because you come back to the equivalence
of it's not really a meaningful
statement to say whether it's me or not
if it has all these properties that
counts as
an individual agent in the reality that
we can be aware of if that makes sense
yeah and I think we I agree if we really
followed this through I think we would
converge to the same point which for me
tends to be well I'll frame this a
little bit by saying something like you
know uh you know Hume we were talking
you're just mentioning earlier about how
like you know Sam Harris said I wouldn't
tell it to my daughter you know Hume
skeptic would question well will the sun
actually rise Etc but he made the point
that basically once he puts his
philosopher pen down and he goes and
leaves his study he's now living like a
regular person now you could say so
there's a there's a potentially
meaningful distinction between the
pragmatism and the sort of intellectual
logical uh you know coherence let's say
but I do think that there's a meaningful
way that we can actually collapse those
in a way that should be collapsed
because
um
because it would lead to something like
uh what information about reality has a
has causal power for sustaining my
viability and flourishing in the face of
entropy right kind of tie back in some
of this free energy principle you know
Bayesian updating sort of thing here
right so
um you know and this is the point that
uh that you introduced me about the work
of like kolchinski and walpert which
I've made great use of of thinking about
meaningful information as being that
meaning that a system uh produces by
processing information about its
environment that ultimately AIDS its
viability right now if what we're
talking about in a pragmatic sense has a
deleterious effect on our viability
because of our Concepts then we might
say that that actually is decreasing our
viability and therefore we might be
inclined to say uh if that's our sort of
Criterion for asserting information as
being an accurate model of reality uh
which I'm not sure of a better one and
we could say that things like skepticism
in solipsism are um uh are untrue on
that ground if that if if that line
makes any sense you could really start
to unpack that but I think that that
might be where we'd ultimately converge
an agreement on some of this points on
some of these points
yeah so five minutes
um I'm gonna have to run in five minutes
unfortunately so I'll just like throw in
a quick a couple quick thoughts um oh
let me just say one sentence
um before I forget
um maybe I already forgot
um
let's see okay go ahead Adam I'll try to
remember it sorry
um that's okay so
um oh sorry yeah when you were talking
about viability like all these
explanations like oh well maybe I don't
have free will but being optimistic has
some positive effect what I'm trying to
say is if the micro scale determinism is
true and we're gonna break that's one
point I want to make there's determinism
when people are saying that word it's
conflating two different things there's
physical determinism that I'm talking
about like micro determinism where
everything is just this model like where
you have these atoms are basically pool
balls and they're following these
trajectories well I'll get to that in a
slide but that's a different kind of
determinism than saying that your genes
and experiences
um uh give rise to what you do
um
my point is if you're saying all these
if the micro scale determinism is true
there's no need to even talk about oh
optimism helps me there's there's no
like oh even being optimistic because
like all that biological level talk is
causally redundant so basically if
there's micro scale determinism
genes even aren't determining anything
that's causal over determinism you're
saying okay the genes cause my behavior
but then you said the atoms caused my
behavior so my point is if micro scale
determinism is true you don't even have
genes determining your behavior it's an
incoherent argument and Sam Harris is
conflating these two types of
determinism and flipping back and forth
so what I'm saying is we got to break
this down and what uh agency what
top-down causation does is it overcomes
this physical determinism and then
there's biological determinism that
determines what agents will do
um and I'm saying that Consciousness and
self-awareness reflective thought is
what overrides biological determinism
and that's when based typically your
higher mind like this monitoring kind of
prefrontal Cortex executive control like
the mind that's responsible for that
there's access Consciousness versus
phenomenal Consciousness distinction so
that mind can override your biological
programming your impulsive actions so
when we have this hierarchical model we
see that there's multiple there's two
types of determinism at least and then
there's multiple types of top-down
causation which overcome those things so
not to say that that argument
doesn't hold up like we have to talk
about determinism as far as like your
you know genes determining your behavior
but my point is if someone believes in
microscale determinism then these higher
level things when people say oh you know
your genes are deciding what you're
doing that would those things would also
be at the phenomenal those would be
shorthands because you could actually
look at the genes and you could see a
bunch of particles and then you could
use newtonians trajectories just applied
to the particles the genes are
phenomenal now the neurons are actually
phenomenal
so it's a level of new I don't know Adam
have you thought about that at all
yeah the um and that's kind of my part
of my agnosticism is like is there such
a thing as a true atomism does causation
even make sense if it's just like an
undifferentiated like uh Quantum field
for instance like as soon as we're
talking about particles or kinds of any
anything we can even name or pick out
um are we basically course screening and
are we in kind of like a
um and and then like when we say micro
uh why don't we just keep going like
isn't it already somewhat like an
instrumental for a given purpose but in
terms of it's like I've been like and
I've kind of kept these separate like
these issues of like the philosophy of
causation like the hammings of Free Will
so like I've tended to focus on like
functional cybernetic Free Will
basically the planning and and like the
the architecture of choice and like
being able to like
um suss out different options and
evaluate counterfactuals that you then
like have different control energy for
the system but I think there could be
really interesting connections between
how we handle causation though and where
within the control hierarchy and the way
you're describing of like were um what's
responsible for what so like ways in
which like system two can override
system one or like that's absolutely
what I want to develop here because I
think you can bridge this low level
causation discussion that I'm talking
about which for example Paul Davis and
Sarah Walker have written about
informational control and that's with
the origin of life there's this change
in the causal structure of the system
and then it gains this agency and that's
what I focused on a lot in part one of
the book
um and so what I'm saying is
Adam's work focuses on basically this
Free Will topic where I'm saying that
there's this even higher level system
Beyond just normal biological agents
that comes with not just Consciousness
but
an ability to create counterfactuals in
imagination so it's like a prefrontal
cortex sort of
higher self
um and a lot of people say that
self-solution that's why I love to fall
back on Adam's work because it really
breaks down the self from a mechanistic
perspective
um but that's exactly what we can do we
can look at the space of counterfactuals
and as we will see that I think there is
some indeterminism at the fundamental
level of reality that propagates up and
that's what you know you see with chaos
even though it's called deterministic
chaos and that's a whole other issue to
get into but basically
um I'm saying that there are choices and
that the world's trajectory is not set
in stone and there's some variation and
when we as agents
um consider the space of counter
factuals and then choose something
specifically
um it may be something like we're going
to make a choice and then our biases
like our impulsive decision is to make a
certain Choice like reflexively based on
like how we feel and you know our
genetic programming and our experiences
but then we can have another process
where we go okay is this decision
optimal given my principles I have this
higher self now I think about like
what's good what I want to do what are
my long-term goals
and that that is the mechanism that
corresponds to what people mean when
they talk about free will
um and so I'm excited about that you
know and and working with Adam to to
explain that to people who you know are
just think that there's no way Free Will
can work because he's looked at the
talks about these mechanisms from this
you know cybernetic and computational
neuroscience perspective and formalize
them people like Sabina hasenfelder like
physicists are like saying there's no
way freaking Free Will can be compatible
with a causal picture of the world I
don't think that's true but what I
wanted you know and Adam's going to
leave so he's unfortunately part of this
but he'll see it later I think we can
Bridge Adam's work at this higher level
to this low-level causation stuff to
actually have a causal story where
there's actually still cause and effect
but there's higher level causation
um that can basically override the sort
of cause the lower level bottom-up
causation and then you even get these
higher levels where you can have
um that sort of causation being
overridden by conscious like mental
causation so you would have bottom
causation and then top down causation
and then mental causation and top down
in mental causation they would all be
like looped under like you know
categorized in a downward causation or
you could call them all top-down
causation but there are differences when
Consciousness emerges that allows for
what could be called new causal power
things are working in a similar way but
you will see a behavioral change when
you get Consciousness that will allow
for
things like technology things that
require imagination uh counterfactual
generation that can't be achieved with
the lower level intelligence
and that we can actually construct a
causal picture that is perfectly in line
with everything we know about causality
but when you do this you realize that
the bottom-up story and I haven't really
defined that you know you guys know what
I'm talking about but I haven't defined
it for their listeners but that when you
have this story of causation you have
agents emerge and they're actually
control centers that can initiate causal
chains and they do it for reasons
there's always reasons that you want to
make a certain decision over another so
some people think because you have a
reason that's a cause that somehow
that's not free will but if you didn't
have a reason for it you would be doing
it randomly and that wouldn't be free
will either so free will just has to be
reconceptualized within this framework
and it's not full free will but full
free will wouldn't be free will in the
in the first place because again it
would be random if it was not based on a
reason but what I'm saying is that your
reason even though it's a Cause
um the reasons uh it's not determined
because basically
um
it's it's not determined in the same
sense that people are talking about with
physical determinism we'll get to this
there's no way I can do it without
looking at the slides but if anyone has
any comments about what I just said
uh and Adam I know you gotta go so any
final concluding thoughts
um I am furious that I have to go but um
I'm really uh I'm looking forward to
tuning in a bit so I'll talk to you soon
all right see Adam thanks for coming
yeah if anybody wants to read Adam's uh
papers on integrated World modeling
Theory and yeah uh cybernetic free will
we can just Google his name in those
terms and you'll see some great papers
and some you know really uh respected
journals like entropy I think is the
integrated World modeling everyone yeah
um Michael no I I was just uh I'm just
trying to again do my job it's uh Daniel
I did want to ask your thoughts about
you know active inter influence or
inference at this juncture
yeah any thoughts about active inference
how that applies to anything we've said
already and I will link it to that soon
because I know a lot of listeners that's
what you're they're interested in
I'll definitely look forward to how you
link it but although active inference is
this incredible modern composable
framework for on one hand cognitive
modeling and on the other hand the
actual embodied situational modeling a
lot of the reason why people get into it
get curious start participating in The
Institute is exactly the topic of
self-help and self-improvement and
personal decision making amidst
multi-scale uncertainty and so there's
among the many gaps between Theory and
application or practice one of them is
utilizing these kinds of multi-scale
information geometry decision making
moment of choice type Frameworks for
what for what we actually do so this is
something that really strikes at the
heart of what we do as infra ants and
I'm just looking forward to how you
frame it in this narrative and then we
can come back to some more technical
details too yeah so we're going to cap
it eight I guess at 7 50 I don't know if
you'll have many questions in the chat
um but I'm gonna try to give the
presentation in the next like 45 minutes
um but feel free feel free to comment on
stuff that will still be helpful but I
guess we shouldn't get too far into like
make a comment so we can mark it I might
give a little answer and then we'll come
back to it but I prefer that you speak
up because then we'll know what to come
back to
um
so I'll say a few more things about
causality because they're important and
then I'll get into kind of the bigger
picture of the theory and then
specifically the self-help teleological
stance which is you know the free energy
principle comes into play there and
um yeah then we can talk about practical
applications for the individual and for
society because the goal is that this
system can be used it's kind of like a
theory of everything so it explains
reality but that it can be used to
improve your life as an individual but
also be used to figure out how to sort
of optimize our social systems political
systems so it kind of creates
a logic that could be used to base like
a new like a political party on like a
third party or something which would be
great if we had a party kind of based on
systems thinking we kind of need a not
like a bipartisan ideology right now
that's not based on anything other than
um
evidence-based things that we know can
be used to to optimize systems not that
that's everything but what I'm saying is
it provides a foundation that then the
ethical
uh and kind of moral
stances emerge from and if you don't see
this basic Cosmic story then you will be
confused about ethical issues and what I
will argue is that folk psychology
ethics all of that stuff it was it's I I
believe
is consistent with this view because it
was kind of intuitive that this is the
story of Nature and that it will kind of
ease that cognitive dissonance for
people who have accepted the
reductionist view
like I know a lot of people have
accepted this view that there's no
agency that there's just the strict
determinism but then they want to use
you know this free energy principle type
things to improve their life but that's
kind of a contradiction because
are they choosing to improve it or is
there just one trajectory that's set in
stone and and and so I think that
getting this stuff straight will allow
people to embrace stuff like the free
energy principle and apply it to their
lives because they go okay this I can
actually use this and I can do that and
I can create change in myself and in the
society I'm a part of but with this old
model there's no hope for change because
there's only one trajectory and so if
Nietzsche really took that seriously it
would be
no reason to really talk about
responsibility because it's just purely
a block time
Frozen thing where the Futures already
determined from the initial State and
the fact that it would repeat over and
over is just even more hell it's like
determinism was bad enough now you have
to experience not having you know an
illusion uh forever
um so what I want to offer is a
different model that we can't fully get
into but what I would what I have called
Eternal recursive emergence and so that
it's not a cyclical process it's
actually a process of the universe
evolving and maybe giving rise
um to something new potentially like a
new universe
um there's cosmological National
selection we don't have to go there we
have to talk about like what what you
know
anything outside of this universe but
um
my point is that
yeah so what I want to show is that the
universe is uh not an arbitrary system
it's not random it is a system that
exhibits a design you can say it's the
appearance of a design maybe it's not
really designed but there's there's
qualities that can't be explained
um if the universe was the only Universe
in all of reality uh uh you you couldn't
have that theory either there's a
designer that designed it that way or
there's a larger reality with a
Multiverse that would explain this fine
tuning and that's where basically
science went they said okay it looks
like there's a Creator because the
fine-tuning problem but we can't accept
that so we have to consider this
Multiverse option but the Multiverse
option is just as weird as a Creator it
leads to all kinds of crazy things like
other universes where there's every
possible version of you
um so it probably has just as much
baggage as the Creator thing but then
there's cosmological natural selection
which basically is an evolutionary
explanation where basically universes
give rise to other universes and there's
this darwinian selection principle that
would lead to like a universe optimized
for like complexity growth in life uh
essentially like spreading like
continuously so we don't really need to
get in those metaphysical topics but uh
I just wanted to State up front that
um the universe does have something that
uh we could call it design but when I
say that don't assume that I am talking
about it being created by some sort of
conscious intelligent agent it could be
this evolutionary process
um but it's not random it's not
arbitrary and that's the big mistake is
that we have models of a random system
like a gas that's what boltzmann used to
kind of
try to have a statistical foundation of
the second law of Thermodynamics and the
problem is we base the Dynamics of that
inanimate system I mean we we understood
the Dynamics of that inanimate system
and then we assume that the Universe
behave the same way and that led to all
of these
um
bad assumptions that created this
nihilistic worldview so let me let me
talk about that first
if determinism is true like if there
were no indeterminism at the lowest
level for example
um everything was just made of these
atoms and these atoms were like
classical scale objects like pool balls
on a pool table
and then you have all these atoms and if
those atoms follow classical
trajectories and they're just like
basically you can imagine the universe
as a table of pool balls
um then there's no room for anything
there's one future trajectory and it's
set in stone
so if you believe that if you accept
that world view
there is no other future there's no
changing it and if you believe that
and you want to change your life you
have to and you're really taking this
seriously you would have to ask yourself
well if I change my life am I really
changing it or was this the way it was
always supposed to happen it was
determined that I was going to change my
life or are you saying like
it's determined in a way where you can't
change your life so you shouldn't even
try it leads to all these weird
conclusions but what I'm saying is
that's not the way reality is and that
leads to like this world view where you
have no agency you can't get around it
because if it's a purely pool ball
universe
then there's no agency
um not only that so that's the first
thing that's if if the world was
Newtonian at the micro level there would
be no agency there would be one
trajectory and there would be this block
time thing it would just everything
would follow from the initial state in a
way that was calculable from just
specifying the positions of every
particle and applying Newton's laws to
those and then we have some forces that
interact but it doesn't really change
the picture
um so
there's just one continual trajectory
then boltzmann found that you know an
inanimate system because all of in a gas
for example so it's a specific type of
system that boltzmann was using to
derive the second law of Thermodynamics
on a statistical Foundation
um and it's not the way open systems
work so first of all we should know that
um
he showed with statistical mechanics
that if you have a gas so in a gas every
particle is uncorrelated it's just
moving around freely and in his model
also people should know that this is
before we understood the periodic table
periodic table didn't come until like
decades after boltzmann did this work so
we didn't understand like chemical
bonding for example we didn't understand
a lot of things so in his model as an
idealization used Spirit spherical like
what would be marbles like spherical
round things that bump off each other
elastically so they just bounce off each
other they don't combine and interact
with forces and if you have this picture
if you if you have these things just
bumping off each other interacting this
way moving around
um following these classical
trajectories
um not bound in any way you will get a
transition from order
um to disorder if the system starts out
in an ordered state of course
because the disordered State there's
more possible ways to do that so if
everything's moving around randomly you
see this trajectory here that we see
um and then so the idea but
there's so much there were so many weird
assumptions in trying to apply to start
Universe like when you start to break
them down like none of them really made
sense so he was saying okay this is what
has to happen you go from order to
disorder
um and this must wait be the way the
universe is because this is what has to
happen by statistical laws if
everything's moving randomly if there's
no magical forces do anything this is
what happens
um so
um
the problem with that
uh uh basically
well so
one thing I should say is that's not
even true if this was the way the world
is
um and people pointed this out to
boltzmann
given enough time if these are following
these mechanical trajectories even the
disordered state will go back to the
ordered State given enough time this is
poincare's uh
um recurrence theorem
um kind of similar to nichi's Eternal
recurrence but so the idea is that if
you have the system behaving this way
you it would um basically all
trajectories are possible and given
enough time it will go from disorder and
then we'll revert and people challenge
both men with this and he couldn't get
away from that that possibility
um what I I lost my train of thought
earlier
um I didn't let you know I just went on
to the next thing but what I forgot to
say was that um
both men was like the face of the
problem of why is our universe look so
complex if it goes from order to
disorder and then that's where like so
he had to say oh it must have started
out really ordered because it can't go
from disordered order so it must have
been this highly ordered state which was
the beginning of time this is low low
entropy state
but now we know that after the big bang
everything was homogeneous and then
things started aggregating so it was
literally an equilibrium State that's
fully mixed up
High disorder State something closer to
that before that and then things started
clumping and you get more organization
so the story is completely the opposite
of what we've been taught Julian Barber
in his new book explains this that the
trajectory of the universe is towards
higher complexity and Order and that we
made a mistake by applying this model of
an inanimate system to the universe in
its entirety when the universe has all
of these batteries in the sky we call
stars and their Driving Systems away
from equilibrium
so then we had
um
Ilia pregogene in 1940 1950 1960 1970 I
would say 50s and 60s were probably when
he was starting this work and it was
really gaining influence
but he basically showed that there's
another Dynamic where if you have a
system of particles driven by a flow of
energy it will start to naturally
organize that system
um assuming that the molecules can bind
to each other so you need to have the
right sort of
um molecular variety for this to happen
but this model of boltzmanns didn't take
into account
bonding it didn't take into account the
force of gravity it didn't take account
into account open systems and what I'm
arguing is ultimately that the
universe's Dynamics are more like an
open system being pushed far from
equilibrium where it's self-organizing
so in this model the universe isn't
going towards a disorder because it's
not a a universe made of particles that
that stay uncorrelated so this Bolton's
model was based on this H theorem where
everything stays uncorrelated but when
things interact they become correlated
so this model works for gases and it
doesn't work for open systems and what
I'm saying is it doesn't work for the
universe we applied it to the universe
and if this was true there's only one
trajectory which means there's no
changing in the future what's going to
happen is going to happen and if that's
the case that's pretty depressing
because it kind of demotivates us to go
oh you know what I can change the world
I can have this idea and it can blow up
like Mark Zuckerberg by creating
Facebook like you could create something
like Facebook and you would have that
and you would change the world world but
if you believed in determinism it would
be kind of strange you'd be like
wait but this is already determined so I
already did it in a way I'm already
gonna do it and like there's only one
trajectory and then I play that
important role in history no that can't
be true I'm not gonna this is impossible
like I'm Gonna Change the World and it
was determined so
that philosophy leads to a lot of
weirdness that I'm saying completely
dissipates when we get the causal
picture straight and we see that there's
not this nihilistic one trajectory
because of quantum indeterminism
and that's not everything but what
Quantum indeterminism does is it shows
that when you shrink when you zoom in
and you get to a certain level that
Newton's Laws of Motion do not hold you
will see there will be no definite
state
uh uh of an electron that you can
predict given its prior State there's
only going to be a wave function that
gives a distribution of probabilities
where that can go and then use the born
rule to find out where it's like you to
go and then if you repeat that study a
bunch of times you'll you'll see these
statistical patterns but so what I'm
saying is quantum and determinism
get rid of this picture of
um
brick determinism at the micro level
and if you did have that strict
determinism at the micro level
you would not have any agency or any
there would be no real counterfactuals
they would be sort of
due to our epistemic limitations what we
can know about the world we think there
are different possibilities but there
actually are none the world can only go
one way and what I'm saying is that
there are some different there's a
possibility space of things that can
happen and that when agents make
decisions you're carving out a path
um that in some way is not it's not
determined by the micro scale physics
because of quantum and determinism and
then we have chaos too at the classical
scale where you can't predict what a
chaotic system is going to do people
call it deterministic chaos I have
issues with calling that determinism
because it's completely not predictable
and I don't even think determinism is
the right word people want to look up
norden's Dome if you have a ball posed
at the top of the Dome there's multiple
Newton's equations that can satisfy
where it's going to go next there's
actually even determinism is not fully
deterministic but that's kind of beyond
what we'll get into so
um
let me just try to go faster through the
slide since it's 7 20. so I'm not going
to talk about a lot of the details that
uh I planned but maybe are earlier
uh conversation provides context that
can clear a lot of this stuff up so what
I'm arguing is that the universe is
self-organizing and so Lee smolen uh
popular physicist says the possibility
of conceiving the universe as a whole as
a self-organized system in which a
variety of improbable structures exist
permanently without the need of a pilot
or other external agent
um I can't see that word
um so we have the possibility of
constructing a new scientific cosmology
it's clear that if the natural state of
matter is chaos and external
intelligence is needed to explain the
order and beauty of the world
um so he's basically saying if we had
this model of like Randomness and it
wouldn't make sense for us to see what
we see and we would need it a Creator
would be a better explanation but if
life order and structure are the natural
state of the cosmos itself then our
existence indeed our spirit might
finally be comprehended as created
Naturally by the world rather than
unnaturally and in opposition to it
and you'll see up here that he says a
variety of improbable structures
um that exists permanently so what I'm
saying is there's some language issues
here that we're seeing
um where we're saying why do we see all
this improbable stuff if it's there it's
not improbable so it's only improbable
if we accept the old model uh based on
you know this simplified model of
causation that doesn't include top-down
causation which we'll explain and that
actually complexity
that you would say that this is highly
improbable that complexity just keeps
growing and growing and growing because
statistically you would think that there
would be some transient complexity and
then basically you would have this trend
towards entropy that you know this
complexity would dissolve what I'm
saying is it's not when I'm saying that
the universe is becoming more and more
complex it's not opposed to naturalism
it's that our conception of naturalism
is based on an outdated Paradigm that
did not include dynamics that really
exists that were now just finding so
that this these structures that are
highly complex were never improbable and
I'm actually going to argue that they're
statistically inevitable
um
uh that they arise
in a way deterministically and it might
be kind of confusing that I use that
word but what I'm going to try to argue
is that there when we talk about
determinism we need to make distinctions
between that as well so what I'm saying
is that there's strict determinism is
not true but I'm now going to argue that
something like Global determinism is
true which is a name that's been used by
philosophers that there is that there
are attractors that create these
Dynamics such that it is natural that
the world goes towards increasing
complexity and that
if we see this trajectory that we're a
part of you know life is spreading we're
building technology the biosphere has
created all this complexity on Earth if
we spread we're spreading complexity
throughout the Universe in the form of
like you know computational structures
life is a computational structure this
information processing Network that we
call the biosphere is spreading if life
spreads that that was never improbable
it was just improbable because it seemed
improbable because we didn't have all
the laws and that actually it's
inevitable
um but that there is some Freedom within
that but there is an outline that's
basically
um deterministic at this larger scale
um and by that I mean things can go a
different way like if you're around the
tape of time and you played it again
that different events there would be a
slightly different chain of events that
would happen you would get different for
example genetic mutations because
genetic mutation and Schrodinger was the
first person to speculate about this but
that there's a Quantum component so if
you rewound the tape of time and you
played it again you would get some
different genes but what I'm arguing is
because of these emergent attractor
dynamics that were really explained by
non-equilibrium physics and and the work
of the Precision then what you see is
that you would get the same trajectory
towards higher and higher complexity
because there were other laws that we
weren't aware of and so in this model
there's going to be a sort of cosmic
destiny that is this sort of form of
global determinism and then there's
going to be
free agency that the agents can do
things that's not set in stone within
that kind of global deterministic
picture so it's kind of new it's not I'm
saying that it's not binary it's the
world deterministic or indeterministic
there's indeterminism at the lowest
level which basically introduces slack
into the causal chain so not everything
is fully determined in this strict sense
but because of these attractors you get
these emergent Dynamics where you're
going to see similar patterns similar
regularities
um
so Kristoff Coke just a couple
scientists who well yeah I'll skip this
stuff but so there are a lot of
scientists who a lot of philosophers who
have had this kind of teleological
narrative that the Universe was moving
towards some sort of goal that it seemed
to be like an organism that's developing
and that seemed like a an idea post
naturalism people like teal hard day
Chardon and uh bergson where you know
um uh
in Chardon was religious but bergson was
a philosopher that wasn't really so I
think a lot of these people got
criticized wrongly they were actually
seeing what was right about nature but
this view is thought to be
opposed to naturalism that was
teleological and that had to be some
sort of Mystical Force and what I'm
saying is we just didn't know about
certain things we didn't understand
information and that these people were
right and that a lot of people will hear
this and say oh well that's against
science that might be again they might
think it's against the second law of
Thermodynamics or something let's know
there's a big misunderstanding about
that and all of these people are you
know all the scientists on this page
really everyone with the exception of
couples phosphorus are extremely uh
respected and very accomplished people
who support this view I mean all right
Ray Kurzweil you know it's technology
guys a little bit more out there but he
even uses the word destiny destiny
ultimate it is clear that the physical
laws of our universe are precisely what
they need to be to allow for the
evolution of increasing levels of order
and complexity ultimately the entire
universe will become saturated with
intelligence
This Is the destiny of the universe so
what I'm saying is that this is the
trajectory of cosmic Evolution this is
the the road map of the future and this
provides something like an outline for
uh non-reductionist Theory of Everything
based on emergence so you have first
physics and chemistry emerged in biology
then brains in technology and then the
merger of biology with technology and
then you get patterns of matter and
energy and the universe becomes
saturated with intelligent processes and
knowledge so life expands and we do that
because we have to we're going to run
out of energy on this planet our star is
going to die which necessitates that we
move outward and then we extract the
energy from that and we keep moving
outward and as we do the informational
Network that is life keeps expanding and
it keeps
taking inanimate matter in the world and
incorporating that into its
computational substrate so the the
island of agency the island of
information keeps spreading and
subsuming the inanimate world and I'm
saying that that is an inevitable
process and people say well that seems
very unlikely and if that that's
happening then it's it's not part of the
the designer it's not part of the the
the the code of the universe like it's
not necessitated by the the parameters
the laws and the constants they'll say
you know it's just something that could
have happened uh and it's unlikely but
we're defying the odds now when those
people say that they don't even realize
their own ontology like if they believe
in determinism then there's only one
trajectory there's only one thing that
could happen so there's no likely or not
likely if you really believe in
determinism there's no statistics and
there's really no causation it's just
one thing follows another and people
have talked about that if German isn't
true then even causality is an illusion
it's just one sort of Fab of events that
all follow from the initial event
so
um what I'm arguing is that the Universe
shows the Dynamics of a far from
equilibrium system a driven system and
that it moving towards complexity isn't
violating any laws and it's not
improbable
we just didn't understand far from
equilibrium Dynamics and that the
universe's complexity doesn't have to be
transient so Sean Carroll has this thing
where he's showing like the increase in
complexity and the increase in entropy
and people go okay this is making sense
complexity is not opposed to entropy
it's part of that but it goes up and
then it goes down you have the coffee
and you have the cream and the the
coffee mixing and you get this
complexity and then it all becomes
homogeneous what I'm saying is no that's
not true for the universe at all
complexity keeps going because when life
emerges it's not like some complexity
like you get some you know random
Pebbles arranged as a crystal and then
the wind blows and then they disperse
life is robust it's modeled the world
and it's because it's modeled the world
it can start to it can maintain its own
existence so for example if an asteroid
is coming at the Earth in 100 years
assuming that we advance technologically
at the rate we've been we're going to
destroy that asteroid we're gonna do
what we need to do to preserve of life
and that's going to change the
deterministic trajectory of the
inanimate world so Life Changes DNA the
trajectory of the inanimate world but
what I'm saying it was inevitable that
life emerges and does this so there is a
sort of trajectory that's sort of set in
stone from the uh initial parameters but
that this trajectory
um is the opposite trajectory of what
boltzmann thought it's actually towards
greater and greater organization
and the discussion of where's the limit
if this universe wakes up and the whole
thing becomes this integrated
computational system when does it have
to stop what about the second law of
Thermodynamics what about the energy
uh needs and I wrote an article for
noema called life need not ever end and
it was shared by David Deutsch and
Sabine Austin Felder and Robin Hansen
also were commenting on it and saying
yes it's possible that life could
potentially not have a limit it depends
on if there's an upper bound to entry
Robin Hansen said Sabine was like I have
a chapter on this in my book so a lot of
the things that we took as gospel like
the first law and second law of
Thermodynamics those apply very well to
certain systems but we shouldn't have
applied them to the universe as a whole
I mean the first law of thermodynamics
is just like
uh there's conservation of energy which
which is
um
holds and we use that to calculate
things but this statement matter can't
be created or destroyed absolutely not
true Cosmic inflation theory has new
matter and energy created during the
cosmic inflation period
um continuously and then now with the
expansion of the universe there's Dark
Energy constantly being created as well
and astronomers I mean there's this
astronomy conference paper where people
have speculated have argued that we can
use dark energy and that's getting more
speculative
um uh to continue to to power life we
might not even need that if you read my
article you'll see this but you can look
up on Sean Carroll's blog he has an
article called Energy's not conserved
and it talks about basically the first
law is not true in the way some people
thought it was
um oops I didn't mean to do that
let me go back to this slide
so um let's speed it up
um so maybe this is where we're at now
so it's a series of these
um stages and what I'm saying is we're
at this stage and that the biosphere
um mirrors a brain it's an Information
Network of Agents exchanging information
through the internet
and that there's actually you know
people might say that's Cosmic mysticism
well there's some interesting new
theories by people like Lee smallen and
John Lanier
um arguing that the universe is a
learning machine and everything in that
paper is consistent with this view so go
read that paper read the universe as a
neural network by Vitali he has a group
on Facebook and we've been meeting
um we're taking a break for the summer
and making some videos but basically
there's
a mathematical foundation for this
this picture and uh so calling it Cosmic
mysticism is just not true anymore and
you can have a fundamentally purposeful
Universe headed towards this what tr day
Chardon would describe as like an Omega
Point
um and it's completely consistent with
naturalism as long as you update
naturalism to include these new Dynamics
so
um I was going to talk about phase
transitions so basically this these
stages in Cosmic Evolution occur from
components like Nature's fundamental
particles combining to make higher level
systems so we have you know Adams uh
come together to form molecules which
come together to form cells which come
together to form organisms and
ecosystems and in the biospheres this
fully Integrated Network so those are
phase transitions it occurs in stages
you have a depiction here we see a
single-celled organism uh and then those
organisms you can think of a slime mold
so you have a bunch of like paramecium
or something and they need to solve a
problem and so they come together and
they solve a problem they form uh
multicellular organism so here's a slime
mold and here's a human
and these agents also come together to
form larger collectives and every time
you have one of these it's called a
phase transition and it's exactly the
same as the phase transitions
not exactly the same but the same
category of
phenomena like when you have
um
water freeze into ice but we have these
non-equilibrium phase transitions where
you'll have like the emergence of a a
tornado or a whirlpool in your bathtub
um and basically these little units like
in the formation of a Whirlpool you have
all these atoms that are bouncing around
chaotically and due to some
thermodynamic constraints that we won't
get into here they start to organize
themselves into these uh Collective
formations that create these flow
patterns and you can see these organized
structures and that life is basically
another version of this
um and that when
um atoms come together to make a
our subatomic particles come together to
make an atom like these phase
transitions they continue in the
hierarchy of life so you have agents
coming together single settlements doing
multicellular then to make societies and
these phase transitions
um
happen at this edge of chaos so there's
this sort of dialectical dynamic between
Order and Chaos that creates complexity
and really
everything is going through these Cycles
so when there's a phase transition you
know you don't want to a system to be
too stable because it's too rigid to
transition to the next stage so there
will be periods of chaos like we're
experiencing right now in society and
you might think that the world's ending
but it's actually an indication that a
phase transition is about to happen and
so the system has the potential to
either collapse or to transition into a
higher state of organization
and so you know this shows this these
different stages you have non-living
then you have it with living you go from
cells military organisms to tribes
and cities Nations and in tagaya and
then it can even extend from like when
we terraform Mars that's the bias for
yourself replicating and so life will
basically
the spread of life is like this higher
level unit that's the biosphere making
copies of itself with variation in
selection and then you know life would
potentially you know
um I'm arguing inevitably subsume
um Galaxy uh solar systems than galaxies
uh and so on
so
let's skip some stuff and get into the
the self-help stuff since we don't have
much time Daniel are is it a eight do we
have to cut it eight or can we go 10
minutes longer
we can go 10 minutes over well we'll
only go 10. um I don't want to keep you
too long but that will help with the
questions if I can end at eight then we
can do 10 minutes if questions are maybe
I'll try to in before but um so these
phase transitions create these memory
systems so these higher organized
systems
um like life uh
uh so when we get the first cell
we have genetic memory and that's
encoding information
that the organism basically that living
things have discovered through Evolution
so evolution is this process where it's
making these different copies of these
organisms
um so there's a genome with some
information but it makes a copy and that
copy has some variation so you get
something different and that difference
that organism might be better fit to the
environment or Worse fit if it's worse
if it's a worse fit it's going to die
out so it's going to be weeded out that
that template of information is going to
be weeded out of the population and the
the the organisms that are well adapted
get to make more copies of themselves so
what's going on in this process is that
you're building up information in an
organism and that information
corresponds to adaptations and so that
information is information that is
predictive about the environment
so organisms are performing inference
from the very beginning of life's
emergence they're trying to solve a
problem it's how to stop this order to
disorder transition basically for an
organism to stay organized it has to
find energy
and if it has to find and that's what
Schrodinger's book what his life was
showing is that you know life resists
this tendency to fall apart that both
men describe because it captures energy
and that energy allows the system to do
work that's keeping the organization so
with these phase transitions you get
different memory systems building on
each other so you have genetic memory of
the origin of life then you have neural
memory with the emergence of brains and
then you have the emergence of
civilization and you get cultural memory
and then you get meme propagation so you
get a different mode of transferring
information and
um all of these memory systems build on
each other and they all encode
predictive information about the
environment that allows the living
system to stay out of thermodynamic
equilibrium to stay out to prevent
falling apart
um so one thing that is worth mentioning
is this new picture of hierarchical
emergence this new paradigm where you
have this multi-level level nature of
reality where reality is organizing
itself into these hierarchical levels
it has predictive power that the
reductionist theory any reductionist
theories of everything don't have those
are are micro physics theories and they
don't apply to life so those theories of
everything I would argue aren't theories
of everything because they don't include
life and civilization and Consciousness
and what I'm saying is that that stuff
has causal power it's not epic phenomena
so those things any Theory of Everything
needs to include those things because
they consider them epic phenomena they
go we don't have to worry about it but
what I'm saying is those things actually
have causal power they need to be
explained so some predictive power that
this theory has that the old model
doesn't this micro scale model is that
we can actually use the Dynamics of a
system at one level to understand the
Dynamics of the system at another level
because they're isomorphic they're they
have similar patterns because they're
all complex adaptive systems so what I'm
saying is that you can make predictions
and you can
use principles to optimize society that
are the same principles at work and
evolution that optimize organisms
and so we can think about someone's
asking okay maybe you accept that
there's a global brain you go okay we
are agents we're informationally
connected we're exchanging information
the way neurons exchange uh you know
signal each other through Action
potentials we must be forming this
collective intelligence the way that
there's an intelligence in the brain and
we know we are because that's how we
build rockets and stuff the single
person doesn't do it we build on
accumulated knowledge we stand on the
shorter of Giants and we share
information that's what science is all
about it depends on that so
if you want to ask
what how intelligent is
the global brain is the network of
humans then you can fall back on
understanding the way that
neuroscientists have understand brains
and what leads to greater computational
power in brains or
is what's the most robust design for a
civilization well what's the most robust
design for an organism
well we want it to be hierarchical
because you have this division of labor
and all these other advantages that
we'll talk about in a minute but so my
point is this Theory allows us to
predict things that we couldn't predict
before because we are using a model of a
similar system of a complex adaptive
system at one level to tell us things
about what hasn't happened in the future
and what will emerge and so there is a
an Essence there is a aspect of
determinism here it's not the same kind
of determinism but there's a global
determinism where you get expected
patterns at these levels so we can get a
glimpse into where the future is headed
but we can never know the details and we
can never know what will emerge exactly
but we can see that these phase
transitions happen and we will get new
emergences
um
talking about predictive power so Paul
Krugman Nobel prize winning Economist
said by 2005 it will become clear that
the internet's impact on the economy has
been no greater than the fax machines
probably the most wrong statement that
you could ever make
um and so
um why did he make this mistake here we
see it again internet maybe just a
passing fad as Millions give up on it
why did they make this mistake what I'm
saying is if they had this framework
that I've just outlined we would have
known when we saw the internet this is a
tool for interconnection this is a tool
for complexification it's not going away
maybe the internet would go away but
something else with a different name
would replace it because this is part of
this trajectory that Ray Kurzweil called
like the Destiny for life
so without this Theory we will not see
obvious things that would be obvious to
us otherwise and we'll make terrible
predictions like Paul Krugman and
hopefully everybody reminds him every
day of his life that he made that
prediction
um he is into he's really into systems
thinking and so I think he would
understand this and I'm interested to
know whether he got into systems
thinking after he made that prediction
or before because if you see this
picture like teal hard dish Arden's
newest fear he predicted this the
internet like you know 100 years ago
um based on his theory
becoming more integrated
um
so what does this mean for society we'll
mention some of that stuff before
getting into the Bayesian stuff just
because it's here isolationism is bad we
want to be connected if you cut people
off it's not good um there's no
information exchange and it could be
good for your nation in the short term
but eventually
what's happening elsewhere in the world
is going to affect you because it's one
integrated system so we want to connect
to people because we want to open up
channels of information exchange but we
also want to uh preserve Nations we want
to have this hierarchical thing where
there's
um control centers at all of these
levels towns cities Nations uh
Etc so we don't want it to become a
homogenized hive mind why because
complexity is in computational power
it's a function of variety and
integration so something is more complex
has more computational power if there's
more diversity among the parts and if
there's more
um
connections between those parts so that
definition of complexity that lets us
know if an organism is more complex like
a human brain is more complex than an
ant brain because it has more neurons
and more connections and more
hierarchical levels we can use that to
create a more robust Society now what
does this mean for you it means life's
part of a cosmic process with a goal
there's this Cosmic attractor and we're
agents that are part of that bringing
that attractor about
this process allows the universe to to
wake up so life spreading is the
inanimate world
finding a form that models itself and
slowly the the universe starts to become
this Integrated Network that's this
coherent intelligence so that's pretty
interesting
um spiritual implications to that
however you want to interpret that but
when we're part of this what does it
mean for us okay so this is the framing
of the free energy principle it says
organisms are so saving it for last so
it'd be climactic so the free energy
principles it frames it with this
Schrodinger Framing and Carl friston
that's where he got it from and it's
also influenced by cybernetics but if
you look at that stuff you have the free
energy principle because it basically
says all organisms will fall apart all
ordered systems so free energy principle
applies to aliens any any organized
system anywhere in this universe will
have to first of all extract energy if
they want to stay organized uh the free
energy principle doesn't focus on that
but even though it has free energy in
the name but I will focus on that
because I think you should be a part of
it organisms have to capture real
thermodynamic free energy to stay in the
game of existence
to capture energy from a chaotic
external world
you have to start modeling the world and
that evolution is building a model of
the world through variation and
selection through through these
accumulation of adaptations and then
brains do it even better and then you
can update the model in real time with
brains because you have synaptic
plasticity you don't have it's not slow
where things have to die and you have
this phylogenetic learning which is like
the the population is learning this
individuals can learn in real time
and so you have to model the world and
the free energy principle that's what it
says it says there's reality and it has
all these details that we don't know and
we have to create a model or a map of
that world that's a coarse grain
simplified version of that
and then
um that uh
uh model is going to have errors and so
what the free energy principle and
active inference framework says is that
when we're doing actions in the world
those are like miniature experiments and
um what we should do if we want to live
optimally and stay out of thermodynamic
equilibrium if we want to survive and be
robust we want to decrease the
difference between our model of the
world
um uh we want to decrease the error of
our model and we want to make it more of
an accurate representation of the world
so you have reality and then you have a
model of reality and when you want your
model to match reality as close as you
can to be able to extract energy and
avoid threats and to stay in existence
so we can be part of this continual
process of complexification
so we only got 10 more minutes but I
think we can uh actually cover all this
so
this looks really complex but this is
going to allow me to explain the free
energy principle and merge it with
evolutionary theory and even the process
of science so
this is an organism imagine this is the
first organism
um that uh emerged with the origin of
life
and so this organism makes copies of
itself
and you get all of these different
designs right
so these different designs are
variations on this model this organism
is an embodied theory about how to
survive about how to stay far from
equilibrium so it has a predictive model
of the world that makes copies of itself
and you get all of these competing
predictive models and then these models
compete for survival and some die out
and the winning design is the best
predictor it gets to make copies of
itself when you get a similar design
so what's going on here is you have
models that are competing models the way
scientific models compete and Bayes
theorem is basically you have a theory
and you have competing models and then
you make predictions with those models
and then you test those predictions and
you update the probability that each
model is true based on the results of
those experiments
and so you want to update your model
based on new evidence and so what I'm
saying is evolution when you create all
these organisms these copies and they
compete it's competing models the way
that scientific theories compete and the
winning model uh is a product of natural
selection the same way that the winning
scientific theory is a product of
surviving criticism and testing so
that's a natural selection pressure
um so as these Generations go on you get
um with each generation you get an
update to the model it's a Bayesian
update and so the model starts to match
reality better such that after a bunch
of generations you get an optimized
organism that's optimized for that niche
and so this is how Evolution itself is a
process of Bayesian inference as uh
organisms adapt they're updating their
model
Carl fresen has understood this
equivalence and and says that all of
evolution is inference of course someone
might say all inference is evolution and
it would all be equally true but so this
model applies to science and applies to
learning so instead of all these
different organisms you know which we
said could be theories different
competing models you could have this as
different
models of
um maybe you're trying to figure out how
to play your sport a sport like to the
best of your ability and you want to
test out these different things and then
you test them and and one performs
better and so that's the free energy
principle is that you're decreasing the
difference between your model and actual
reality so you're doing these little
experiments all the time and based on
what works you're updating your model or
you should be if you want to optimize
your system for survival and growth and
so
um
it's the same when we're trying to find
a um uh a a political philosophy
capitalism socialism these are competing
models we test those models out this is
variation in selection and the ones that
work they get retained by society and we
keep those so capitalism I would argue
um it's terrible right now but it was
the best model for the time and
um the superior model is always going to
be it's never going to be one thing it's
always going to change so we would want
to test hybrids between socialism and
capitalism and crypto economics if you
want to Def like determine a political
party based on this what you would say
was that the best solution for a
political party is to try out different
models in small areas and uh based on
what works then you can see where to
apply those models but I would argue
that it's not going to be socialism for
every place it's not going to be
capitalism it might not even be a hybrid
it might even be something in addition
to that like I said crypto economics and
that we have to test these things and if
we're not testing them and we're not
trying these different models we're not
living optimal we have no way to get uh
to the to the to the optimal worldview
political philosophy if we're not doing
this testing in Bayesian updating so
that's one big thing another thing that
you know as I said you know this is a
basis for a self-help system so you have
to model the world and your model of the
world how accurate is determines how
successful you are in life if you don't
have an accurate model of the world you
don't understand how
things work for example let's say you
take a bunch of physics courses you can
become an engineer and if you don't
understand how things work and you're
not paying attention to evidence and you
just have some sort of belief that you
believe for no reason and you try to get
through life you will not be able to
achieve goals and progress uh in the way
you would if you were doing Bayesian
updating
um
so
when I say this is a self-help system
basically I'm saying there's lots of
inaccuracies about our model of the
world that could be
optimized if we took a Bayesian approach
to reality and let me see let me tell
you what I mean by that in these last
few minutes so we have five more minutes
so
there's this principle of incomplete
knowledge that comes from cybernetics
and it says our there's this phrase the
map is not the territory so our model of
the world is not the same as the actual
World it can't hold all those details
the world is too chaotic
uh and there's just too many
um there's too many variables for any
brain to model so we need to have this
low-res like coarse grain version of our
motto of the world and it's going to be
incomplete it's always going to have
uncertainty so anyone who's certain
about anything like Sam Harris is 100
certain that Free Will can't exist even
though there's a lots of uh
well-respected people that know a lot
more about him than neuroscience and
causality that say that Free Will can
exist
um it's just bad to be that certain
because anybody who's been that certain
in the past has been proven wrong
everybody thought Newtonian mechanics
would explain everything then we had
general relativity and now we see
general relativity doesn't explain
quantum mechanics every model is going
to be proven wrong so one thing to do is
never be fully certain always take into
account the uncertainty of your model
what should we do from that we should
consider all possible theories
um we should consider for example when
we're trying to explain something we
want to know what was the call what was
the origin of covid we want to know how
did we get sick the other day okay we
want to know how dangerous dangerous it
is is it to move into this neighborhood
um when we want to try to understand
like the origin specifically like we
have to consider all possible
explanations because if we don't we're
already setting ourselves self up for
bias and self-deception so we want to be
aware of the space of possibilities of
of possible explanations for a certain
thing when making a decision and then we
want to
map out the likelihood of each of those
theories being true with all everything
we know
and we do we don't we can't do this in
everyday life we don't need to we have
intuition about you know what to do in a
lot of simple situations but with
complex situations like what person we
should vote for what political candidate
what political party we should
um support uh I think you have to do uh
this sort of Bayesian analysis where you
map out every possibility for example
every possible Theory and explanation
for something you write down the
evidence for each one and then you use
those theories to make predictions and
then you test them and then you
um based on the results of those testing
uh that testing update your likelihood
of each of those theories being true and
we're not doing this all the time so let
me give you some examples
um
well so
flat earthers you could you know flat
earthers think the Earth is flat they
have these pictures where it's just
flatter uh in space and you know so if
you go by this method I'm not gonna I'm
not gonna
rule that out immediately uh to be a
good Bayesian you want to consider the
possibility because there's always going
to be surprises in nature who would have
thought quantum mechanics who would have
thought superposition in tangamon was
real it was so weird that everyone would
have said that was pseudoscience they
would have been like that defies the
laws of physics we don't know so we
consider the theory and we write down
evidence for it then we try to test it
so we can take a flat Earth where we say
we'll do a test let's put you in a
rocket we're going to pay for this we're
going to fund this we're gonna give you
a video camera you and your fighter
friends are gonna bring you up in a
rocket we're going to show you we're
going to look we're going to see if it's
round or not everybody's trying to
really figure it out because most of us
haven't been in space
let's say we take them into space we
bring them back down they see the Earth
is round they come back down and they
still get on their flat message boards
Earth's flat they drugged me or
something like that some impossible
thing
um that person is not being baze optimal
because they're not updating their uh
model of the world
um
uh to be more accurate so they're going
to make mistakes let me give you an
example a final example of
um how I can give you some new Knowledge
from this from a theory that will
immediately change statistical Behavior
I want to show you the effects of like
agency so let's say you're completely
ignorant to whether squids or octopus
are intelligent you just don't know and
you're you you eat calamari at a
restaurant every week sometimes you eat
popcorn shrimp and then you eat calamari
let's say it's randomly
and you're a person that cares about
your compassionate person so I have
lunch with you and I say you know
Neuroscience has shown that it seems
like you know squids are highly
intelligent and they show all this
complex Behavior they have these nervous
systems that would uh seem to make them
intelligent
um I mean lead to this like
computational power where they can solve
all these problems and I tell that
person if they're convinced of my
argument
their statistical behavior is likely to
change such that if you're someone and
you were looking at their eating pattern
all of a sudden you see them get this
new knowledge they update their model
and suddenly they don't need uh the
calamari anymore suddenly their
appetizer becomes shrimp because they go
oh that's unethical
um and then maybe they're kind of weak
maybe they go I love Calamine they eat
it like once a month instead of like
every week or something so what I'm
saying is that there's a real power of
knowledge that when you
show the person that and they update
their model their assist statistical
change in Behavior that's quantifiable
immediately
so
That's The Power of of uh of knowledge
like we can we do have like agency and
we can actually see that people are not
behaving in a Bayes optimal way and
um we can see all sorts of you know
disagreements about for example theories
if we did a Bayesian analysis we could
start to converge on what is the true
answer for this
um so it could be a solution to the
misinformation problem the solution to
the misinformation problem is a solution
to a problem in your own life
um basically it tells you you know how
you need to update your model to be more
accurate and then you behave in a
different way you don't have these like
delusions
um
so you know I yeah there's uh you set
goals for yourself uh in the
teleological stance because basically
life to stay out of equilibrium has to
have these intrinsic uh survival goals
like finding energy and avoiding threats
but when you create a goal you you
basically create an attractor and when
you start working towards that goal
um
that is when you have a goal in your
mind you say I'm going to do this for
the world I'm going to build this thing
that creates an attractor that you work
towards if you don't create that goal in
your mind you're actually not going to
do what you need to do to make sure uh
to work towards that happening so goal
setting is absolutely something
essential and if we don't do that then
we're not living optimally either and
actually like the Law of Attraction
those kind of things that sound you know
like woo and you're like you know but
they're these best sellers why do they
sell because we can actually start to
map this on to the this sort of like
um
systems thinking and you can see oh
that's why this new age stuff worked
um variation selection is the method of
evolution or learning or science so we
can use that in our real life like if
you're writing a book or something
um
don't just be isolated for a year
writing it yourself write it a little
bit at a time pass it to your friends
get some criticism and so that's a
natural selection filter they tell you
what's not good about it you go back you
change it you vary it and you give it
back to your reading group that's using
variation and selection to optimize your
writing you can use this for any project
for not doing that we're making life
harder
um creating a collective mind so I'm
saying that there's this process
uh at all these hierarchical levels so
when we
um start to collaborate with someone
we're forming a collective intelligence
that then exchanges information for us
so we want to try to form Collective
minds and that's when you're passing
your book to your friend you're doing
that you're forming a collective mind
and then you're doing an optimization
process at the level of the collective
you want to align interests so you find
Synergy so basically you're not you
don't want to be opposed to others goals
so if you all have goals you want to
look at what are your similar
goals and not where you're conflicting
and then you will try to align those
interests so we could try to do some
sort of analysis with China for example
where we try to uh align interest and
see where we agree before you know
rather than focusing on all of our
disagreements and try to make progress
that way and then the law of requisite
variety is the final thing I'll mention
right now
um is that
um to when you want to model the world
depending on how complex your Niche is
you basically your model matches the
complexity of the niche and so you will
have a lot you will need a lot of
accessible cognitive States if your
theoretical physicist living in
Manhattan in this chaotic world were
living on a farm or something so you
want to try to
um find the niche that Max matches your
skill set
um so you want to find low complexity
Niche if you're not a highly cognitive
person and if you are a person that
thinks a lot and your mind is just
always
thinking you might not want to live in a
small town simple like rural town you
might because you're not match with the
niche you could be highly intelligent
but still you would be seen as crazy
because basically
um the niche is so simple that your
model is too complex so
um yeah there's a lot of things that
come out of this that I would like to
expand on but we don't have any time and
we haven't really talked about
Free Will and and and everything that we
talked about at the beginning so maybe
we'll have to do this again but um
hopefully that was an introduction to
this Theory of Everything which creates
this Cosmic context that you're an agent
in the theological stance is saying I'm
an agent that has to survive in a world
that tends towards this other disorder
otherwise and to do that I have to
extract energy and to extract energy I
have to model the world in more detail
and more sophistication as we run out of
energy we're going to have to model more
and more of the world so Bayesian
inference is how agents basically
um
uh carry out this process of cosmic
conflict complexification so life is the
mechanism for in complexity increase and
we are agents with causal power and we
have to basically
um take this Bayesian approach to get to
the Future uh
that we want to see and if we don't take
this approach
um
basically uh
uh the world is on a sort of trajectory
towards resource depletion so this is
actually like becoming aware of this and
this method is something that Society
needs to get us to the next phase
transition if we don't have it we're not
going to get there so what I'm saying is
that this self-help system in a way
there's a selection pressure that's
creating it it might not be this version
of it but some form of this is sort of
destined to be the next big thing so
everybody thinking along these lines
there are other people besides me
um keep going in that direction because
you're on to something so yeah
Daniel you jumping in there yet or what
I think yeah Brandon must have had to go
wow
well Bobby
I'll ask just two short questions from
the chat just in our final minutes so
first quick question from Ross B
what is the line between living and
non-living matter
how about I answer them in like a few
sentences and we do a little bit more
um but we'll still cut it early so the
line between living and non-living
matters agency an agency comes from the
causal power of information and it gets
built up through an evolutionary process
so you have an auto catalytic set that's
a self-maintaining chemical set and
there's some sort of phase transition
between that chemical set and the first
cell where there's a causal a change in
causal structure and the agent basically
gains informational control and it gains
the ability to initiate new causal
chains and we call that top-down
causation so check out Sarah Walker and
Paul Davies work on informational
control next
all right very well second question from
Ross are these phase transitions
representative of weak emergence or
strong aversions in Bobby's Theory EG's
new laws come into play that exert
downward causation
yeah I wanted to address that nuggets in
the Free Will stuff and I would love to
just come back and do a talk on Free
Will so
um what I'm saying is strong emergence
has been defined wrong it's emergence
that seems to violate the laws of
physics the way it's been defined and
what I'm saying is strong emergence is
real but of course it doesn't violate
the laws of physics anything that's real
is part of physics so
um weak emergence would be more like the
formation of like a whirlpool in the
bathtub like you have all these
uh you have the formation of a coherent
structure that does introduce Global
constraints that constrain the movement
of the particles such that they're no
longer chaotic they're in this ordered
state but with strong emergence you
actually see this change in causal
structure that I just mentioned or
information
basically gains causal power and you
have an agent that's a control center
that's actually deciding to do things
and that's actually real causation
that's called top down causation and so
what strong emergence is is for example
uh prior to Life coming into existence
you have all inanimate matter and when
you have a living thing we already said
you drop a rock and a pigeon off a tower
one's predictable from Newtonian
equations one's not one you have to
understand it's genes and you have to
understand like its relationship to its
environment and then you can say oh it's
flying because it has to survive and you
can actually predict some things about
it won't Splat on the ground it's going
to fly away but you can't predict it
with the same thing so what I'm saying
is what strong emergencies is the change
in causality such that we have living
agents with informational control and
it's not something that's against the
laws of physics or somehow working
against that what it is is the laws of
physics weren't complete now we're
understanding that there's information
that can have causal power and you do
see this different type of causation
such that the Living World behaves
distinctly different than the non-living
world
Michael the penultimate word
oh that's uh put me on the spot young
Lads uh and again Daniel you know uh
what's going on in the background and
I'm sure people will guess but uh no um
I think you know what uh Bobby and I had
spoken about earlier was uh
this comes down to what is our uh
personal agency in terms of you know
again Bobby has spent a long time here
and I'm gonna have to like re-listen to
it myself again and uh spend some more
time with it but
um we're elucidating or Bobby is
elucidating uh what kind of agency we
have in the face of complexity
um and obviously there's a what we say
before Bobby a methodology is a
methodology to this uh we had some kind
of Catchphrase whatever but yeah so well
the thing is we do have agency we behave
different than inanimate systems and we
do have causal power
um but that's not enough that's like the
first step it's like okay where are
these agents then what do we do and the
the Bayesian approach is kind of an
instruction manual for how do you do how
do you exercise this agency agency
optimally
and what we want to do is we want to be
aware of the uncertainty in our model
and we want to try to decrease that
uncertainty and we do that by for
example not just having one theory about
something we consider all possible
theories we consider the outcomes of
those theories and we make sure that we
update our model uh in light of new
information and if we don't do that
we're not behaving optimally and we're
not fully exercising our agency and
you're going to see consequences of that
at the societal level and so Society is
basically creating pressures that are
going to force us to be sort of
Bayesian agents because if we're not
updating our model and not seeking out
new information and being curious uh
we're not going to be competitive
but yeah it's all about agencies I will
add to this too Bobby just know what to
bridge the gap between the two of you
um uh Daniel and pin out the word for
sure on my part but uh you said act
infer and serve right
Daniel said that I like that yeah
yeah so all this is really saying new is
that active inference is not something
specific to humans that organisms when
you have a population of organisms and
evolution is making all these copies the
population is doing a sort of inference
process you have these different
organisms that are different embodied
models and then they're competing and
then only the most accurate ones survive
so that's what Bayesian inference is
um and uh this should also apply at the
level of society so when you have a a
social organism a society it has a model
and that model is its worldview it could
be a religion it could be the political
model it could be authoritarianism or
whatever and so with that too we want to
optimize those models and if we don't
try all of the different models and and
test those models
um we will have no way to know if we
have the optimal model so we can't just
go capitalism seems the best or
capitalism sucks let's throw it out
Let's do let's do communism we want to
test things constantly and update and
that's error correction if we don't do
that we're screwed so
the Bayesian the free energy principle
needs to be extended to all these levels
um and when we do that then we have a
whole new way to go about optimizing
social systems and political systems
right now it's just like oh I think this
you know I believe in
uh you know a liberal world or I believe
in this conservative View and it's like
okay fine well how do we get to the
bottom of it No One's Gonna agree first
I mean let's do do testing constant
testing the proof is in the pudding it's
a good idea we're going to see benefits
we're going to take surveys of everyone
and get feedback and see what we can
improve and um Vitality of insurance the
guy who has the idea of the universe
being the snail Network which has been
covered by media he's explained that
this multi-level learning is consistent
with this neural network Theory and that
you do have true emergence and you have
causal power at these higher levels
um and he's trying to design a political
party around this like a new approach to
politics and
that sort of position that I came up
with that you need to test it without me
even saying anything to him that was
already his idea that he's has fleshed
out you know I'm sure more than I have
um so people are working on this stuff
but this is like a new Niche being
created right here this is the time
everybody needs to go like how can we
use these systems
Bayesian inference and evolutionary
science evolutionary theory mechanisms
to optimize Society if we don't do that
from if it's not entering the political
discussion
we're lost we're primitive like like in
a hundred years all of these things that
we're talking about I believe will be
part of the discussion uh uh for anyone
who's having any sort of ideas about how
to design systems
all right Bobby well you're always
welcome back for 15.4 we can push into
decimal places
unseen all right let's do Free Will
let's let's bring Adam and everybody
back and and do Free Will Free Will and
does voting matter two sides of the same
coin
yeah it is and no one's really doing
that no one's thinking that that's
debate has they think it's purely
intellectual it's not yeah so yeah we
need to connect it to practical stuff
yeah well thank you to all of our
panelists and Bobby as always so
yeah both of you yeah no strengthen the
journey journey well is everyone
listening all right I wish yeah I wish
we could hear more from Brennan but uh
yeah we'll follow up um uh go to the
road to Omega sub stack and I'm gonna
post about this video and then we can
have some discussion in the comments if
you see this yeah all right thank you
all right thanks a lot everybody
farewell bye